good afternoon everyone welcome to 213
大家下午好，欢迎213
it's good to see you just a reminder
它的好，看你只是一个提醒
that your attack lab is due tonight at
你的攻击实验室是由于在今晚
11:59 p.m. you have one great day for
下午11:59 你有一个 伟大的一天
this for this lab and cache lab we'll go
这对于这个实验室和缓存实验室里，我们会去
out and write about the same time now
并写信大约在同一时间
it's going to be a little tight for cash
这将是 现金 有点紧
lab it'll be due next Thursday so you
实验室它会由于下周四，所以你
might want to you might want to get
可能想你可能希望得到
started on that soon b2 last lecture we
开始 不久 B2上一讲我们
learned about the memory hierarchy and
了解了存储层次 和
the idea of caching today we're going to
缓存的想法今天我们要
look at a very important kind of cache
看一个非常重要的一种缓存
which is a which are called cache
这是一家 被 称为缓存
memories and they're very important to
回忆和他们对我们很重要
you as a programmer because they can
你作为一个程序员，因为他们可以
have such a big impact on the
对这么大的影响
performance of your program so if you
你的 程序 的性能，所以如果你
know about the existence of these cache
了解这些缓存的存在
memories and you know how they work as a
回忆和你知道他们的是如何工作的
programmer you'll be able to take
程序员，你就可以拿
advantage of that in your programs
利用这一点 ， 在 你的程序
so last time we looked at that the
所以最后一次 看的
memory hierarchy is a collection of
内存层次是一家集
storage devices with smaller costlier
具有较小昂贵的存储设备
devices that the and faster devices at
设备 的更快的设备
the top and slower cheaper and much
顶部和较慢的便宜，多
larger devices at the at the bottom and
在较大的装置在底部和
then at each level in this hierarchy a
然后在这个层次中的每个级别
the device that level K serves as a
该等级 k作为该装置
cache holds a subset of the blocks of
高速缓存保存的块的子集
that are contained in the device at the
被在包含在设备
lower level at level K plus-1 now recall
在级别k 加-1现在回忆较低水平
the general idea of caching so we have a
缓存的总体思路，所以我们有一个
memory array of bytes and it's it's we
字节的存储阵列， 它是 这是我们
break it up arbitrarily into a
打破它任意成
collection of blocks and these this
块，这些本集合
memory is larger slower and cheaper and
存储器是较大的慢和更便宜和
so it's and it's much larger than a
所以它和它比 一个 更大
cache which is smaller faster and more
缓存是小更快 ， 更
expensive and which holds and which
昂贵的，并且，其保持并且
holds a subset of the blocks that are
认为是块的子集
contained in the main memory and then
包含在 主存储器中 ，然后
blocks are copied back and forth between
块被复制之间来回
the cache in the memory in these block
在这些块中的存储器高速缓存
size transfer units so for example if
大小传送单元，从而，例如，如果
our program requests a word that's been
我们的程序请求 一直一个字
contained in block number 4 it asks the
包含在块号4它要求
cache to to sent to return the word
高速缓存发送到返回字
that's contained in block 4 the cache
多数民众赞成在含有4块高速缓存
looks and it's at the blocks that it's
外观和它在它的块
the subset of the blocks that it's
块的子集，它的
towards discovers that block 4 is not
朝发现块4不
there so it asks the main memory to send
有那么它要求 主存储器 发送
it block 4 which it does and I and then
它块4 其中它不和 I和然后
when it when that block arrives at the
当在该块到达它
cache the cache stores if it potentially
如果潜在的缓存缓存存储
overwriting some existing block
覆盖现有的一些块
similarly if if our program asks for a
同样，如果如果我们的程序要求的
data word if that's contained within
如果这是包含在数据字
block 10 the cache looks sees that it
块10 缓存 看起来看到它
doesn't have that block so it requests
没有该块，因此请求
that block from memory which copies it
从存储器块中其拷贝
into the cache
到高速缓存
which overwrites an existing block now
现在 将覆盖 现有的块
subsequently if if our program asks for
随后，如果如果我们的程序要求
a request or if our program references a
或者，如果我们的程序引用一个请求
word that's contained in block 10 for
该中都包含的块10字
example then the cache then we have a
例如那么缓存 ，然后 我们有一个
hit and the cache can return that block
命中和高速缓存可以返回 块
immediately without going to the
立即而不去的
expensive operation of contacting memory
接触存储器的昂贵的操作
and fetching that block from memory now
现在从存储器中取出该块
there's a very important class of
有一个非常重要的一类
thought of caches these so called cache
缓存这些所谓的高速缓存的思想
memories which are contained in the CPU
其包含在CPU中的记忆
chip itself and are managed completely
芯片本身和完全管理
by Hardware and they're implemented
通过硬件和他们实施
using fast SRAM memories and the idea
使用快速SRAM存储器和想法
for this cache which is is right next to
这个缓存是紧挨着
the register file is to hold frequently
寄存器文件 是经常举行
access blocks or blocks from main memory
从主 存储器 存取块或多个块中
that are accessed frequently okay so
被频繁好了，所以访问
hopefully because of the principle of
希望因为原则
locality most of our requests for data
当地大多数 我们对数据的请求 的
will actually be served out of this
实际上将被送达了 这 一点
cache memory in a few cycles rather than
在 几个周期缓存而不是
in this set rather than from this slow
在这个集合，而不是从这种缓慢
main memory
主内存
now cache memories are managed
现在高速缓冲存储器的管理
completely in Hardware so this means
完全硬件因此，这意味着
that the heart there's there has to be
该心脏 有必须有
Hardware logic that knows how to look
知道如何 看 硬件逻辑
for blocks in the cache and determine
在高速缓存 ，并确定 块
whether or not a particular block is
是否一个特定的 块是
contained there so cache memories are
包含有这么缓存记忆
have to be organized in a very kind of
已经在一个非常样的组织
strict simple way so that the logic the
严格简单的方法，这样的逻辑
lookup logic can be pretty simple so
查找逻辑可以很简单，所以
this is very all cache memories are
这是非常所有的缓存记忆
organized in the following way you can
通过 以下方式组织的，你可以
think of that you can think of the cache
想想，你能想到的缓存
as an array of s equals to the s sets
为s的阵列等于给S集
each set consists of e to the to e lines
每个组由电子商务到到e线
where each line consists of a block of D
其中的每一行由D的块的
it equals 2 to the D bytes of data a
它等于2到 数据a 的 d字节
valid bit which indicates whether these
这 表明这些是否有效位
these data bits are actually the bits
这些数据位实际上是位
and the data block are actually
和数据 块实际上是
meaningful right it's possible they
有意义的权利有可能 他们
could just be random bits like you know
可能仅仅是 随机位像你知道
when you first turn on the machine
当你第一次打开 机器
there's nothing in the cache but those
没有什么在缓存中，但这些
bits will have values right the ability
位将有值权的能力
to be ones or zeros but they won't
是一或 零，但他们不会
actually correspond to data okay so the
实际上对应于 数据好所以
valid bit tells us if these if these be
有效位告诉我们，如果这些如果这是
fights actually mean anything and then
打架实际上意味着什么 ，然后
there's some additional bits called the
有一些额外的比特称为
tag bits which will help us search for
标记位，这将有助于我们寻找
blocks which I'll show you in a minute
该块我会告诉你在一分钟内
now when we talk about our cache size
现在，当我们谈论我们的高速缓存大小
we're referring to the number of data
我们指的是 数据的数量
bytes that are contained in blocks and
中包含的块 的字节 和
so each cache has there's s sets there's
所以每个缓存有有s设置有
e e blocks per set and there's B bytes
ee值每块集合和有乙字节
per block okay so the total cache size C
每块好了，所以总高速缓存尺寸为C
is s times e times B okay now so there's
为s次; 乘以B 现在没事所以有
a lot of terms to sort of keep straight
很多术语 来排序保持 挺直
and it's very easy to get to confuse the
它很容易去迷惑
difference between lines and blocks and
线和块之间的差异
lines and sets okay so we'll go through
线并设置好了 ，所以我们将通过
some examples and hopefully these will
一些例子 ，希望这些意志
start to make more sense now let's look
开始更有意义， 现在让我们来看看
at in general how we how the cache
在一般的我们如何如何缓存
Hardware implements a read so when our
硬件实现读，所以当我们的
program accesses when our program
程序访问时，我们的计划
executes some instruction that
执行一些指令
references some word in memory the the
在内存中引用了一些字的
CPU sends that address to the cache and
CPU发送一个地址到高速缓存和
s and it asked the cache to return the
S 和它要求高速缓存 返回
word
字
the word at that address and so the cash
在该 地址类的话现金
takes that address this would be a
获取该地址，这将是一个
64-bit address in case of x86 64 and if
如果在86 64 和壳体64位地址
it divides the address into a number of
它划分地址为 多个
of regions which are which are
其是它们是区域
determined by the organization of the
通过对组织确定
cache okay they're determined by those
缓存还好它们是由那些确定
parameters s that's the s the number of
参数s那是在 S数
steps a the number of lines per set and
步骤a 每组的行数和
B the size of each data block so the low
乙每个数据块的大小，以便在低
order bits there are B low order bits
阶位有乙低位比特
which determine the offset in the block
其确定在块中的偏移量
that that word starts at the next s bits
那这个词开始在下一s 位
are treated as an unsigned integer which
被视为无 符号 整数，其
serves as an index into the array of
用作索引的阵列
Seth can remember we just think of these
赛斯还记得我们只是觉得 这些
as think of this cache as an array of
因为觉得这个缓存作为数组
set the set index bits provide the index
设定的设定索引位提供索引
into the into this array of sets and
入到该阵列 的集合和
then all of the remaining bits all of
然后所有剩余 位的全部
the remaining T bits constitute what we
剩余的t比特构成了我们
call a tag which will help us when we do
调用一个标签，这将有助于我们，当我们做
our search so the cache logic takes this
我们的搜索 所以缓存逻辑借此
address and it first extracts the the
解决它首先提取了
set index and uses that to as an index
设置索引并使用该 作为指标
into this array to identify the set that
这个数组来识别的一组
if this block is in the set I'm sorry if
如果此块是 集合 对不起，如果
the data word if the block that contains
如果块包含数据的字
the data word at this address is in the
在该地址的数据字是在
cache it's going to be in the set
它缓存将是在集合
denoted by the the set index okay
由该组索引表示好
so first it identifies which index to
所以第一它识别哪个索引到
look in
在看
and then it checks the tag it checks all
然后它会检查它检查所有的标签
of the lines in that set to see if
在 该组 的 线路 ， 看是否
there's any any of those lines have a
有任何这些线路中的任何一个都
matching tag that a tag that matches the
匹配的标签，一个标签相匹配的
the T the tag bits in the address okay
经t 在地址 标签位 好吗
and if any checks to see if the valid
如果任何检查，看是否有效
bit is turned on so if those two
位被打开，所以如果这两个
conditions hold if there's a line
条件成立，如果有一条线
anywhere in the set as of where the
在设定为任何地方的
valid bit is is one and there's a
有效位是一个，有一个
matching tag then we have a hit okay
匹配的标签，然后我们有一个好打
then the block that we're looking for is
那么，我们要寻找的块
contained in this set okay if we once we
此集合中包含没关系，如果我们一旦我们
determine that with that we've we've
确定与我们已经我们已经
identified the block then the cash uses
然后，确定该块现金用途
that the low-order B bits to determine
该低位 B个比特来确定
where that where the data we're
这里是其中数据我们
interested in begins okay within that
内 的兴趣开始好吗
block all right let's look at a more
块没事，让我们来看一个更
specific example for a the simplest kind
一个最简单的一种具体的例子
of cash which is when e equals one when
现金是当E等于一个时
there's only one line per set okay so a
这里只有一条 线每设置 好了，所以一
equal one one line per set this kind of
每套这样的一个平等一行
cash is called a direct mapped cache so
现金被称为直接映射缓存等等
here we have a sets each set consists of
在这里，我们有一个 套每套包括
a single line and now the pro suppose
单行 ，现在亲假设
our program references the data item at
我们的程序引用的数据项在
a particular address the CPU sense that
特定地址的CPU感觉，
address to the cache the cache takes
地址到高速缓存会缓存
that address breaks it up into these
该地址将其分解成这些
into these three fields and then for
为这三个字段 ， 然后
this particular address
这个特定的地址
the block offset is four and the set
块偏移量是4和该组
index is one and then there's some tag
指数是一个，然后有一些标签
bits which we'll just denote with with
我们将只表示与位
the color pink
粉嫩的颜色
so the cache extracts the set index
所以缓存中提取了一组索引
which is one and then it uses that as as
这是一个，然后它使用 如作为
the index into the set
该指数进入设置
and then it can just it just ignores all
然后它就可以说，它只是忽略所有
the other de set de block we're looking
我们正在寻找其他的去集德块
for is is in the cash it's going to be
对于是在它的将是现金
in this inset number one then it does
在此插图 头号那么它
the comparison of the tag dips and the
标签的比较骤降和
valid bits and assume that they assume
有效位，并认为他们承担
that valid bits on and that it matches
在和它匹配 的有效 位
then it looks at the block offset which
然后它看起来在 块偏移量
is four and which tells it that the the
为四个，这告诉它 的
four by four by ten suppose that that's
四乘四十倍假设这
what the instruction was was referencing
什么是指令引用了
the four byte in begins that offset for
在四个字节的开始，对于偏移
so now the cache takes take this int and
所以现在的高速缓存会借此 int和
it sent it back to the to the CPU which
它发回 了对 CPU，其
puts it in the register okay if the tag
把它在寄存器 没关系，如果标签
doesn't match then the old-line if the
和不匹配 的旧线，如果
tag doesn't match then there's a miss
标签不匹配，则有一个 小姐
and in that case the cache has to fetch
在这种情况下， 高速缓存再去捡
the the block the corresponding blocks
的块中的相应块
from memory and then overwrite this
从存储器中，然后覆盖该
block in the line and then it can serve
块在一行，然后它可以充当
then it can fetch it can get the word
那么它可以读取它可以 得到的字
out of out of the block and send it back
淘汰掉块 ， 并发送回
to the processor you know let me ask you
到处理器，你知道让我 问你
a question just to see if kind of check
问题只是 为了看看 实物支票
to see if you're following along with
看看，如果你有以下沿
this so if there's a Miss and the cache
此所以，如果有一个 小姐和缓存
has to request the block from memory
必须请求 从 存储器 块
fetch it from memory and then overwrite
从 存储器中 取出它 ，然后覆盖
the block in the current line does it
在当前行中的块 做它
also have to change the tag dips or two
还必须更改标签骤降或 两个
those stay the same so does the do the
那些留相同的，所以不会在做
tag bits that were in this line get
那 是在这 条线标记位 获得
overwritten with a different value or is
用不同的值覆盖或为
it the same
它同
same different save different now why
同样现在不同了保存不同的原因
would it be different
这将是不同的
we haven't changed yes I'm sorry
我们没有改变是的，我很抱歉
Olek it almost certainly has different
Olek几乎可以肯定有不同
data but does it have a different
数据，但它有一个 不同
address exactly it missed it missed
地址正是它错过了错过
because the tag it missed because the
因为它错过，因为标签
tag didn't match
标签不匹配
if the valid bit was false and the tag
如果有效位是假的，并且标签
match then then that would also be a
匹配，那么那么这也 将 是一个
miss oh then you wouldn't okay that's
错过哦，那么你就不行 那
right that's okay good good good okay
右没关系佳好 佳 好
great all right let me do a little let
伟大没事让我做一些让利
me do a really simple specific example
我做一个非常简单的具体实例
of how a direct mapped cache works III
直接映射高速缓存是如何工作的III
want you to understand in real detail
要你真正了解详细
how this would work but I also want to
这将如何工作 ，但我也想
make a point for about the weakness of
做点关于弱点
direct mapped cache --is and why why you
直接映射缓存--is，为什么，为什么你
would want to have more than one line
希望有多于一行
per set okay so we this is a really
每设置好了，我们 这是一个非常
simple our met we have our memory system
简单我们遇到了，我们有我们的记忆系统
consists of 16 bytes okay so it's not a
包括好 16个字节，所以它不是 一个
very useful system with 4-bit addresses
有 4位 地址 非常 有用的系统
and and it's broken up into blocks of 2
并且，它的分解成 2块
bytes each our cache consists of 4 sets
每个字节缓存我们共有4套
with one block per set
每个组的一个块
now our 4 by our 4-bit addresses because
现在我们4我们的 4位 地址，因为
be equal to that's 2 to the 1 we only
等于这是2到 1，我们只
need one block offset bit right there's
需要一个块 偏移位权有
only 2 bytes in a block so the byte
在这样的字节的块 只有 2字节
we're looking for is either at 0 or 1
我们要寻找的是无论是 在0或1
okay because we have 4 sets we need to
没关系 ，因为我们有4套，我们需要
set off set index bits and then the
掀起设置索引比特，然后将
remaining bits are always tag bits in
其余位总是标记位
this case there's just one tag dead all
这种情况下， 只是一个标签的所有 死亡
right now let's
现在，让我们
let's suppose that our program executes
让我们假设我们的程序执行
instructions that reference the
引用的说明
following memory addresses zero one
下列存储器地址零 一个
seven eight and zero and these
七八零和这些
references are reads that they're
引用读，他们是
reading one byte per read okay like I
每读一个字节读好 喜欢我
said this is a really simple system so
说这是一个非常简单的系统，
let's look at what happens now we start
让我们来看看现在会发生什么，我们开始
out Arte are initially are our cache is
出艺术最初 是我们的缓存
empty valid bits are all set to zero and
空有效位都设置为零，
now the cache receives the request for
现在高速缓存接收到用于请求
the byte that's at address zero so it
这就是在地址零所以它字节
extracts the set index bits which in
提取组索引位，它们在
this case are zero zero so these so it's
这种情况下是零零散所以这些所以它的
going to look in set zero four and in
要在设置 零四个在 看
this case since valid is zero it's just
这种情况下，由于有效为零它只是
it's a Miss okay so it's etches that
这是一个好小姐所以它是蚀刻
block from memory sticks the block so
从存储器块粘块，以便
this memory this is the decent this is
这种记忆，这是不错的，这是
using array notation for memory so this
使用阵列符号为存储器所以这
is like the the byte that extend from
就像从延长字节
offset zero to offset one inclusive in
零偏移抵消一个包容性
memory the tag bit is zero and the valid
内存标签位为零 ， 有效
bit is 1 ok now the next the next
位为1点确定现在下 下
address that comes by is for address 1
自带的地址是地址1
well that's a hit right because we set
嗯，这是一个正确的打击 ，因为我们设置
block the block that contains the byte
阻止包含字节的块
and address 1 is already in the cache
和地址1 已经 在缓存
the tag and the tags match okay so we're
标签和标签没关系匹配所以我们
good that's a hit you now we get address
好那你现在我们得到的地址一击
7 so the cache extracts the set index
7，从而高速缓存中提取所述一组索引
bits which in this case are 1 1 or 4 or
位，在这种情况下是 11或4或
3 rather looks in set 3 there's no valid
3，而看起来组 3有没有有效
bit so that's a Miss and it loads the
位，所以这是一个小姐和它加载
data for memory that spans
对于 存储器跨越 数据
bytes 6 & 7
字节6 和7
and in this case the the tag that is
在这种情况下， 该标签是
zero okay so we record that we record
零好，所以我们记录，我们记录
that in our metadata
在我们的 元数据
okay the next reference that comes by is
还好自带由下一个引用
8 now 8 has a set index of zero zero
8现在8 具有零 零 一组索引
zero but that's currently occupied by
零但是这 目前占用
block zero one and we can tell that
零 块 一个， 我们可以告诉大家，
because address 8 has a tag of 1 and the
因为地址 8具有的1和一个标签
existing block of the block at the
现有的块的块在
earlier address at address 0 has a tag
在地址0更早地址有一个标记
of zero so that's a Miss so now we have
零所以这是 一个小姐，现在我们有
to go fetch the block containing byte
去获取包含块字节
number 8 into memory so now we have
8号到内存中，因此现在我们有
bytes 8 & 9 and we in our new tag did
字节8和9，我们在我们的新标签做
okay now the next instruction is for
现在没事了下一 条指令是
byte 0 and we just we just replace we
字节0，我们只是我们只是 更换我们
had that it we had that in our cache and
有它，我们有在我们的缓存和
we just replaced it so so it's another
我们刚刚更换它，所以它的另一
miss so that's unfortunate and it's the
想念所以这是不幸的，它是
only reason we missed it is because
唯一的原因，我们错过这 是 因为
we've got just one line per set and so
我们已经有了每套 等只有一行
we were forced to overwrite that that
我们被迫覆盖该说
block containing bytes the block 0 1
包含块字节块0 1
when we when we missed on on block 8 9
当我们的时候，我们错过了上块8 9
okay so this and you see there's plenty
好了，所以这一点，你看有很多
of room in our cache we've still got
房间在我们的缓存 我们还有
we've got two two lines that we haven't
我们已经有了，我们没有 二 两线
even access right so we our cache is
即使访问权限，所以我们我们的缓存
plenty big but just because of the sort
很多大，但只是因为那种
of the low associativity of our cache
我们缓存的低相关性的
and the sort of the pattern the access
和排序模式 的 访问权限
patterns that we were presented with
我们赠送了模式
we've got a miss that really was kind of
我们已经有了一个 小姐真的是种
unnecessary so oh yeah sorry
不必要所以噢对不起
six so when we referenced when we
六岁的时候，我们引用时，我们
referenced a seven it's actually the
引用了七它实际上是在
it's at offset one in that block six
它在 该块6一个 偏移
seven okay since our blocks are two
7点你，因为我们的块两个
bytes they'll always start on an even
字节他们会一直开始在偶数
multiple
多
any other questions okay so this so this
任何其他问题好了，所以这个所以这
sort of is the reason why you have
排序就是 为什么你的理由
caches have higher associativity higher
缓存具有更高的 相关性 更高
values of e so let's look at and so for
电子商务值，所以让我们来看看 ，并因此对
for values of e greater for values of e
用于 为电子的值E时 的值
greater than greater than one we refer
大于一大于我们参考
to them as a way associate set
他们 作为方式来关联集
associative caches so here e equals two
相联高速缓存所以这里Ë等于 二
so it's a 2-way it's 2-way associative
所以这是一个2路它的2路相联
so let's let's suppose we have a a 2-way
让我们，让我们假设我们有AA 2路
a 2-way associative cache so here we
2路相联缓存，以便我们在这里
have we have our array of sets and now
有，我们有我们的台阵 和现在
each set contains two lines okay instead
每组包含两行，而不是没关系
of one line and suppose we're presented
一条线的，并假设我们介绍
with an address with the following form
用以下形式的地址
we're looking for the word that begins
我们正在寻找 开头 的单词
at an off set of four inside our block
在 我们的块内关闭组四
at within set number one okay so the
在中集头号 还好使
cache extracts that set index so this is
即设置索引，所以这是缓存中提取
set 0 this is set 1 this is set to
设置0 1 这被设置为 将其设置
throws away all the other sets and now
扔掉所有其他组和现在
in parallel it searches it searches the
并联它搜索它搜索
tags it searches for a matching tag in
标签则搜索 匹配的标签中
both of these both of these lines and
这两种都这些行和
anti valid bits so if we get a matching
防 有效 位，所以如果我们 得到一个匹配
tag and a valid bit true then we've got
标签和有效位真的，那么我们有
a a then we've got a hit now that yep
AA那么我们必须得一击即是的
yep
是的
oh it's a very good question so there's
哦，这是一个非常好的 问题，所以 有
this hardware logic that does that
，做，这个硬件逻辑
compare and it's and that's the reason
比较和它的，这就是原因
that as as the number of as the
作为为作为数
associativity goes up that logic gets
关联上升这一逻辑得到
more and more expensive okay it's like
越来越贵好滋味
some like you're kind of doing some kind
一些像你那种做某种类型的
of tree search and so that actually is
树搜索的 ，因此， 实际上是
the limit that's why I mean because in
这就是为什么我的意思是 ，因为在 极限
general right that if you take this to
一般权利，如果你拿这个去
the limit there's just one set with
极限 这里 只有一组用
there's just it's we call that a fully
这里还有这是我们称之为 全
associative cache so there's just one
联想缓存，以便有只有 一个
set and now any block a block can go
设置和现在的任何块的块可以去
anywhere right there's no constraints
任何地方的权利没有限制
now where you place a block but the
现在，你把块，但
because of the complexity of that that
因为那复杂性
fully associative search those are very
完全关联的搜索那些很
rare in fact you do see will see fully
罕见其实你看到的 将完全看
associative caches caches but their
联想缓存缓存，但其
software caches okay so in software and
软件缓存好了 ，所以在软件和
so the the complexity the hardware and
所以在复杂 的硬件和
sort of doesn't doesn't doesn't it's not
那种不不 不它不是
worth it's not worth the complexity of
值得不值得的复杂性
the hardware for the penalty of having a
硬件用于 具有的 惩罚
lower associative 'ti okay but there are
较低的联想“钛不错，但也有
some systems later on when we study
一些系统后，当我们研究了
virtual memory the in a virtual memory
虚拟存储器中的虚拟存储器
system the DRAM serves as a cache for
系统中的DRAM 用作高速缓存
data stored on the disk and as we saw
数据存储在磁盘上，正如我们所看到
last time the penalty for a miss if you
最后一次的惩罚 ，如果你 一个小姐
have a cache on DRAM and you miss and
对DRAM高速缓存和 你错过和
you have to go to disk the penalty is
你必须去到磁盘 的惩罚是
huge for that and so because of that
巨大的为等 因为如此
it's worth it's worthwhile having very
这是值得拥有 很是值得的
complex searches search algorithms in
在复杂的搜索搜索算法
particular in a virtual memory system
特别是在一个虚拟存储器系统
that the DRAM is implements a fully
该DRAM是实现了充分
associative cache where blocks from disk
相联高速缓存，其中从磁盘块
can go anywhere we'll get into that
可以去任何地方，我们会得到成
later when we look in virtual memory but
后来 当我们在虚拟 内存，但
you're right you'll see in real systems
你说的没错，你会在实际 系统 中看到
nowadays that the number goes up right
如今这个数字上升 右
because feature sizes are going down and
因为特征尺寸 的 下降和
designers can afford to implement more
设计师有能力实现更
expensive hardware but the the largest
昂贵的硬件，但最大
of
的
tivity on Intel systems that I know of
tivity的，我知道的Intel系统
is 16-way associative l3 caches and then
16路相联L3高速缓存 ，然后
the others are 8 way associative so
其余8 路关联 等等
that's sort of the order of magnitude
这就是那种量级的
that's state of the art right now ok so
这是 最先进的 ，现在好了，所以
then once we've identified a match we
那么一旦我们确定了我们的比赛
use the set offset bits in this case
使用的设定偏移位在 此情况下
we're accessing a short int so 4 is the
我们访问了一个短整型所以4是
offset within the block of this the 2
这2块内的偏移量
byte short int which then we can return
字节短整型，然后我们就可以返回
to the processor alright so let's do
到 处理器 好了让我们做
that same simulation that we did before
我们以前做的是相同的 仿真
but this time with a 2-way associative
但这次与 2路相联
cache now memory system is the same but
现在高速缓存存储器系统是相同的，但
now instead of one set we have two sets
现在 ，而不是一组，我们有两套
and I mean I'm sorry instead of four
我的意思是我很抱歉，而不是四个
sets we have two sets so the cache this
集我们有两套所以缓存此
is the same sized cache but we're just
相同大小的缓存，但我们只是
going to organize it differently instead
去不同的方式组织它，而不是
of one way instead of a direct mapped
的一种方式 ， 而不是 直接映射
cache with four lines containing four
缓存中含有四个四行
lines one line per set we're going to
行每套一条线， 我们要
implement a 2-way associative cache
实现2路相联缓存
where we have two sets with two lines
在这里我们有两套两线
per set okay so each case is just four
每设置好了，所以每一种情况下也仅4
there's four total lines question
有总共四个行质疑
and it was like oh so that that comes in
样子像哦，使得进来
with the request somehow and I actually
与请求不知何故居然和我
don't know the details of that it may I
不知道的细节，它可能我
guess there so it could ask for just
想有这样它可以请您提供
there could just be a default sighs
有可能仅仅是 一个默认的叹息
maybe it's always it's always a 64 by
也许它永远它总是一个由64
word and then the processor extracts
字，然后将提取物的处理器
that the current bits I actually don't
当前位 其实我不
know the details of that but it either
知道这一点，但 它的细节 或者
comes in on the request or or there's a
进来的 请求或或有一个
standard there's a standard size that
标准有一个标准尺寸
the processor then parses out we'll just
然后处理器 解析出我们只是
assume that the cache knows the wood
假设缓存知道木
size to return yes how do you decide
尺寸为yes返回你如何决定
which block to your place that's that's
该块你的地方就是这样的
a really good question so there's a lot
一个很好的问题， 所以有很多
of different algorithms the most the
不同的算法 的大部分
most common algorithm or a common
最常见的算法或共同
algorithm is least recently used so by
算法最近最少使用这样的
locality you want to keep the you want
地方你要保持你想要的
to keep blocks in the cache that are
保持块是缓存
being used a lot and so if a block isn't
被使用了很多，因此，如果一个块不
referenced for a long time by the
由长时间引用
principle of locality by sort of the
通过排序 的 局部性原理
inverse locality principle it's likely
逆局部性原理很可能
not to be addressed referenced in the
不要 在解决引用
near future so so that's one that's one
不久的将来 ， 所以所以这是一个这是一个
algorithm that you just keep track of
算法，你只是跟踪
and and I'm not showing that there needs
并且，我没有表现出 有需要
to be additional bits in the line to
要附加位在线路
sort of keep like sort of virtual
有点像保持那种虚
timestamps that but that's that's a
时间戳 这一点，但就是这样的一个
that's sort of the general way you do it
这就是那种 你这样做 的 一般方式
just try to keep the things that are the
只是尽量保持属于的东西
blocks that are being accessed the most
正在 访问 的最块
frequently the most recently yes
经常最近是
okay the question is what determines the
还好，问题 是什么决定了
block size that's determined by the
该年代由预定的块大小
design of the memory system so that's a
存储系统的设计， 所以这是一个
that's that's a sixth parameter of the
这是这的第六参数
memory system so when the Intel
存储系统，所以当英特尔
designers decided to put cache memories
设计师决定把 高速缓冲存储器
on their processors they decided that
他们的处理器，他们决定
the block size would be 64 bytes sorry
块大小将是64个字节遗憾
so the block size comes the block size
所以块大小来块大小
comes first then then you determine how
自带第一，然后再确定如何
big you want your cache to be okay and
大你希望 你的缓存是可以的，
then and you determine the associativity
那么， 你确定关联
okay and then once you determine the
没关系，然后，一旦你确定
associativity and you know how big your
关联性，你知道有多大的
cache is then that determines the number
缓存然后确定数
of sets okay
套 好
so basically all of those the the the
所以基本上所有那些的了
number of lines and the cat and the
行 数 和猫和
capacity the number of lines per set is
容量每组线的数量 是
sort of a sixth high level parameter
排序第六高电平参数的
design parameter the size of the cache
设计参数缓存的大小
is a is a high level design parameter
是一个为高电平的设计参数
and then the number of sets then is
然后组数然后是
induced from from that okay yes
从这样行不行是诱导
that's that's yeah how does so that's
就是这样的呀怎么所以这
that's the replacement policy how does
这就是替换策略 如何做
it so question is how does it when
它所以问题是怎么做 的时候
there's multiple lines in a set how does
还有多条线路在一组怎么做
it determine which to over-over right
它确定 过度过 右
and that was what that was the previous
那是什么，这 是以前的
question probably maybe I should have
问题 大概 也许我应该有
repeated it so you try to pick a line
重复它，就尽量挑线
that that was least recently used so
那这是最近最少 使用，因此
lines lines that haven't been accessed
没有被访问的行线
recently are good candidates for
最近都不错的候选人
replacement because because of the sort
因为更换，因为那种
of inverse locality principle right that
逆局部性原理正确 的
they haven't been inversed referenced
他们没有被反转引用
recently chances are they won't be
最近，机会是他们不会
referenced again it oh yeah there's
再次引用它哦耶有
additional bits that I'm not showing
额外的位，我不是展示
here that you have to so so when you
在这里 ，你必须 这样，所以当你
replace a line in the set if that data
替换一条线在所述一组，如果该数据
has changed then it has to be written
已经改变 ，那么它 已经被 写入
back to memory and that's another good I
回到记忆 ，这就是另一个很好的我
haven't shown yes ah so the so yeah so
还没有表现出是啊所以所以是这样
this is a really this is really tricky
这是 一个真正的，这是 真正棘手
parameter right it's a it's a high level
参数正确这是一个 它是一个高层次
system parameter that's that it goes on
系统参数就是它的推移
for years
多年
so the idea you want to have blocks in
这样的想法，你想有块
order to exploit spatial locality right
为了利用空间局部性权
think about if you're going to go to the
想一想 ，如果你打算去
trouble of if you have a Miss in cache
如果您在 高速缓存 中的小姐 的烦恼
and you're going to go to the trouble of
而你要去的麻烦
going all the way to memory to get some
一路去记忆得到一些
data you want to you want to amortize
你想 你的数据要分期偿还
the cost of fetching that data by
通过获取该数据的费用
fetching more than one byte that's
取多个字节这
that's the motivation for blocks because
这对块的动机，因为
by by the by the principle of locality
由由局部性原理
in spatial locality in particular if you
在特定的空间位置 ，如果你
reference a word inside of a block
参考块的内部的字
chances are you're going to reference a
机会是你要引用
nearby word which will also be an
附近的话这也将是 一个
epilogue
结语
okay so blocks the whole purpose of
好了，所以块的全部目的
blocks is to exploit spatial locality
块是利用空间局部性
now if you make your block too small
现在，如果你让你的块太小
then you don't you don't amortize you
那么你就不是你不摊销你
don't get the same amortization right
没有得到相同的权摊销
you maybe get one you bring the block in
你可能得到一个你所带来的块
so there's a reference you get a mist
所以有你雾参考
you bring the block in there's another
你把块有另一个
reference nearby you get a hit because
附近你参考得到一击，因为
the blocks are memory but then the next
块 是存储器但随后的 下一个
reference is in a different block
参考是在不同的块
because your block sizes are too small
因为你的块 大小太小
so you kind of want to make blocks big
让你有种想使块大
as big as possible but without slowing
尽可能地大，但没有放缓
the system down so if you made your
关闭系统，所以如果你做了
block size too big it would just take
块的大小太大，将只取
too long to bring that block in plus
过长 带来的是块加
plus now your block that your blocks are
再加上现在你块，你的块
taking up bits in your cache memory so
占用位 缓存内存中 ，以便
now there's no room for other blocks
现在有没有空间的其它块
right so it's a really it's a really
右所以它是一个真正的这是一个非常
tricky design problem right and I if
棘手的 设计问题，正确的 ， 我如果
we're doing it's taking an architecture
我们正在做它采取的架构
class then we would we would sort of
类的话，就要将我们 的排序
dive into the you know how how
潜入你知道如何如何
architects make those design decisions
建筑师让那些设计决策
but in general that's what it's kind of
但总的来说，这就是它的种
a balancing act right there any other
一个平衡的行为的权利有任何其他
questions yes
问题是
Oh
哦
the question is every time there's a
问题是，每次有一个
myth do you have to do you have to
神话，你必须做你 必须
select a victim line and overwrite it
选择一个受害线和覆盖它
yeah I don't know of any caches that
是啊，我不 知道任何高速缓存的那
that don't do that now we'll see when we
不这样做，现在我们要 我们 什么时候见
look at writes we'll see there's an
查看 写入 我们会看到有一个
option of whether we're only looking at
我们是否 会只盯着 选项
reads right now but with writes that
读，但现在与写道，
question does come up and if if you
问题就来了，如果你
waited in a couple of slides we'll go
等了一对夫妇 的幻灯片，我们会去 的
over
过度
we'll go over that any other questions
我们去了任何其他问题
okay so let's look at this this two-way
好了，让我们来看看这这种双向
associative cache now there's there's
相联高速缓存现在有有
one block offset bit we only have two
一个块偏移一点 ，我们只有两个
sets so that we only need one set index
集，因此我们只 需要 一个指标
and then the remaining two bits are
然后将剩余的两个比特
tagged so let's go through our trace so
贴上标签 ，以让我们 通过 我们的跟踪，这样
address zero has a set is in set zero
零地址有一组是集零
right here that's a Miss so we load that
就在这里，这是一个 小姐，所以我们加载
into memory with the reference to
与参照 存储器
address one that's in set zero and
解决一个是在设置零和
that's a hit because that that byte is
这是一个打击，因为这 是一个字节
in is in our block the reference to
在为我们的块参考
seven is a Miss that's in set one so we
七等于一个小姐那是在一个组，所以我们
load that and we were just picking
加载，而我们只是挑选
randomly tick one of these two over
随机剔这两个中的一个以上
right because they're the cache is empty
正确的，因为他们是缓存为空
the next reference is to address number
下一个参考 是为了 解决数
eight which is in set zero now here's
其中八个是集零 ，现在这里的
here's the difference between the direct
这里的直接 的区别
mapped cache and this too late set
映射的高速缓存，这为时已晚集
associative cache when we when we
相联高速缓存，当我们的时候，我们
reference address eight that block has
参考地址8该块 具有
to the corresponding block has to go
相应的块已去
into set 0 because of this 0 set index
到因为 这个0集合索引 集0
bit but we've got room now because we
位，但我们有空间，现在因为我们
are set to have room for two lines
被设置为具有 空间两条线
instead of one so when we load that in
而不是 一个，所以当我们加载 在
well if we have an available empty slot
那么，如果我们有一个 可用的空闲时隙
we'll put it there we won't overwrite
我们把它放在那里，我们不会覆盖
anything right so if possible always try
任何事情的权利，所以如果可能 总是试图
to overwrite empty empty lines
覆盖空的空行
so now we've got in this set we've got
所以现在我们在这个组已经有了我们已经得到了
block 0 1 and block 8 9 so when we get
块0和1块8 9所以，当我们得到
our reference to block to address 0
我们参考块地址0
whereas before with the when we had a
而在此之前与当我们有一个
conflict miss in the direct mapped cache
冲突未在直接 映射缓存
now we can we can satisfy that that
现在我们可以，我们能满足这一说
request it hits in memory and we can the
要求它击中在内存中，我们可以将
cache can satisfy it from from the cache
缓存可以从缓存中满足它
instead of going to memory ok so that
而不是去记忆 OK，这样
makes sense ok now what about writes so
有道理 OK现在 大概 写 什么 ，所以
there's multiple copies of the data
有数据的多个副本
right we're subsetting as we move up the
对，我们 的子集划分我们动起来
hierarchy we're creating subsets of the
层次结构，我们正在创建的子集
data in the caches so what do we do if
在高速缓存 所以我们做什么，如果 数据
we do a write to a word within a block
我们做了写一个字块中
that's currently in the cache ok we have
这是目前在缓存 好的，我们有
we have two options we can write that
我们有两个选择，我们可以写
block immediately to memory right we're
立刻 拦截 到 我们 的内存 权
we've got a block that's like this big
我们已经有了一个块是如此之大
and we're updating a little chunk of it
我们正在更新 它的一个小块
so we can we can either do the update
所以我们可以，我们可以 做的更新
and then flush it to memory immediately
然后它立即刷新到存储器
so that memory always mirrors the
让记忆总是反映了
contents of memory always mirror the
的存储器内容总是反映
contents of the cache ok but that's
缓存的内容确定 ，但认为是
expensive right I mean you know memory
贵 权我的意思是，你知道内存
accesses are expensive the other so the
访问是昂贵的其他所以
other option is what what's called write
另一种选择是什么什么叫写
back
背部
so in this case when we write to a block
所以在这种情况下，当我们写一个块
in the cache we don't we don't flush it
在缓存中，我们不不刷新它
to memory until we elect that particular
到内存中，直到我们选出特定
line as a victim that's going to be
行，那将是一个受害者
overwritten and only then only then when
覆盖才把只有当
we're just we sort of defer the writing
我们只是我们有点推迟写作
to memory until the last possible minute
到内存中，直到最后一分钟
we defer it until just before the cache
我们推迟到只是缓存之前
would overwrite that that data block ok
将覆盖该数据块确定
so that's called write back and for
所以这就是所谓的 回写和
write back you need to have some an
写回，你需要有一定的
extra bit in the line that indicates
在表示线条额外位
whether that that blocks been written to
这是否是块被写入
so the algorithm is when when the cash
所以算法就是当现金
identifies the particular line to
识别特定的线
overwrite it checks the dirty bit on
覆盖它会检查脏位
that line if it's set then it writes
如果它被设置该行 然后将其 写入
that data to back to disk if the if the
这些数据如果备份到磁盘，如果
data hasn't if that block has a good
数据还没有，如果该块具有 良好
written there's no point there's no need
写有没有点有没有必要
to write it back because it's the same
把它写回，因为它是相同的
it has the same value as the copy of the
它具有 相同的 值 的副本
block on disk ok now so what about so
在磁盘上的OK块现在 又怎么样了这么
that's a right here now what happens if
这是这里 发生了，如果 现在什么是正确的
we have a right missed so we're doing a
我们 有一个 正确的 错过 ，所以我们正在做一个
right to memory and the word that we're
正确 的记忆和我们的字
writing is is not contained in any block
写入不包含在任何块
that's in our cache so we have two
这是在我们的高速缓存，所以我们有两个
options we can do what's called write
选项我们 可以做什么叫做写
allocate so we can treat it if if
分配所以，如果，如果我们可以把它
there's a Miss we can do sort of the
有一个小姐，我们可以做排序 的
symmetric thing that we did with it with
我们做了与 它 对称的东西
the hit which was create a new a new
命中这 是创建一个新的一个 新的
line possibly overwriting an existing
线可能覆盖现有
line and then write in so we could so we
行，然后 写这样我们就可以，所以我们
could create that cache enter that cache
可以创建缓存输入缓存
line fetch it from memory and then do
行从存储器中取出它，然后做
and then do the do the right ok so this
然后执行做正确的 确定，所以 这
is sort of symmetric to reads right that
是那种对称的 ，以读取正确 的
so every right if it misses when the
所以每一个权利，如果它错过当
right finishes the that block will be in
右结束该块将在
the cache and if we do a subsequent read
高速缓存，如果我们做一个后续读
we get a hit ok so that's that's the
我们得到一击 好了，所以这是这样的
reason you might want to do that the
原因你可能想要做的是，
other option is just to don't allocate a
另一种 选择是 只是为了不分配
an entry in the cache don't allocate a
在缓存中的项目不分配
new line just write write the data
新行只写写入数据
directly to memory you don't really need
直接内存你并不 真正需要
to understand the distinction between
理解之间的区别
these two things different caches use
这两件事情 不同的缓存使用
different policies for your own mental
为你自己的心理不同的政策
model a good model to use is just to
模型中使用的 一个很好的模式 仅仅是
assume write back write allocate so just
假设写回写分配所以才
assume that we won't we won't copy the
假设我们不会，我们 不会复制
data to disk if there's a hit we won't
数据到磁盘 ，如果有一击，我们不会
write it back to disk until the last
它写回磁盘 ，直到最后
possible minute and every time there's a
可能分钟，每有一个时间
write miss we'll create a new entry in
写错过，我们将创建一个 新条目
the cache ok so that's that I think
缓存 确定，所以这是我认为
that's sort of the simplest model that
这是那种最简单的模型的 那
it's a reason it's a reasonable model
这是一个原因，它是一个合理的模型
that you can use regardless of the
你可以不管 用
particular cache implementation now in a
现在特别是缓存实现的
real system so far we've only looked at
真正的系统到目前为止，我们 只看到
we've only assumed that there's a single
我们只能假定有一个单一
cache but in real systems there's
缓存，但在 实际系统 中 有
multiple multiple caches so modern core
多个多个缓存 所以现代核心
i7 Haswell architecture from intel
英特尔酷睿i7的Haswell架构
contains multiple processor cores so 4
包含多个处理器核心，以便4
is a typical number for like desktop
对于像 桌面 典型数量
systems 8 8 to 12 it's typical for
系统8月8日至12日这是典型 的
server class systems these processor
服务器类系统中，这些处理器
cores can each execute their own
内核可以分别执行自己
independent instruction stream in
在独立的指令流
parallel and each processor core can
平行并且每个处理器核心罐
contains general-purpose registers which
包含通用寄存器，其
that's level 0 in the cache and then 2
这是在缓存0级，然后2
different kinds of l1 caches the data
不同种 的 L1高速缓存 中的数据
cache the l1d cache and the eye cache
缓存L1D缓存和缓存眼
the L which is the instruction cache and
将L是指令高速缓冲存储器和
these are these are fairly small 32 K
这些是这些都是相当小的32千
bytes they're eight-way associative and
字节他们是八路关联和
they can be accessed in a very small
他们可以在一个非常小的访问
number of cycles the next level of the
循环 的 下一 级别 的数
hierarchy is is the l is an l2 cache
层次结构是 L是L2高速缓存
which is still fairly small 256 K bytes
这仍然是相当小的256千个字节
same associativity and it has a slightly
同样的关联性 ，它有一个稍微
longer access time and and it's unified
访问时间更长，并和它的统一
in the sense that the l2 cache contains
在L2高速缓存中包含的意义
both data and instructions ok so that's
数据和指令 确定，所以这是
all within a single core on the chip and
都在芯片 上的单核 和
then also on the chip but external to
然后还有芯片，但外部对
all the cores and shared by all the
所有的核心，并通过所有的共享
cores is at l3 unified cache which is 8
核心是在L3统一高速缓存是 8
megabytes and 16 Way associative with an
兆字节和16路关联与
access time that's like 40 to 75 cycles
访问时间就像40到75次
so if if there's a Miss in l1 then the
所以，如果如果有一个小姐在L1 则
l1 sensor tries to send a request to l2
L1 传感器试图发送一个请求到L2
to try to try to find the data in l2
尝试，试图找到在L2数据
since l2 is a little bigger maybe maybe
因为L2是稍微大一点，也许，也许
the data hasn't been flushed out of l2
数据还没有被冲洗掉L2的
yet if they'll - can't find it it sends
但如果他们会-无法找到 它， 它发送
a request to l3 to see if they can find
到L3的请求，看看他们是否能找到
the data in l3 if l3 can't find it then
在L3的数据，如果L3不能找到它，然后
it gives up and it goes off chip to
它放弃它熄灭芯片
memory yes question yes name memories is
内存是问题是名称的记忆中
that's it's the DRAM built of DRAM chips
这就是它的内置DRAM芯片DRAM
it's it's separate it's in a separate
这是它的独立是在一个单独的
separate set of chips on the motherboard
在主板上单独设置的芯片
connected by those that i/o bridge that
通过那些I / O桥连接，使得
we and the bus various buses then that
我们和总线各种总线 那么
we talked about last time
我们谈到了最后一次
and for all different for all of these
并为所有不同所有 这些
different caches the block size is 64
不同的缓存块的大小为64
bytes now there's a number of different
字节现在 有许多 不同 的
ways to think about the performance of
的方式来 思考的性能
caches my most most common way is using
缓存我的是最普通的方法是使用
a metric called the Miss rate so what
一个指标 叫小姐率 等什么
this is the fraction of references that
这是引用的馏分
Miss so we're very so I thought and it's
小姐所以我们很，所以 我 想， 它的
1 minus the hit rate so typical for
1 减去命中率如此典型的
caches to work then this rate has to be
缓存的工作 那么这个速度必须 是
pretty low and and fortunately because
相当低和 幸运的，因为
of locality these Miss rates are low
当地的这些小姐率低
another another metric is the hit time
另一另一个指标是命中时间
so if if we do have a hit in the cache
所以，如果如果我们确实有在高速缓存中的命中
how long does it actually take to sort
多久它 实际上采取排序
of look up the you know do the lookup to
看起来了，你知道做查找到
determine that there was a hit and then
确定有一个命中， 然后
return the value okay
返回值好吗
so for for l1 and in a Intel system this
所以对于L1 和在英特尔系统中，这
is four clock cycles ten clock cycles
是4个时钟周期10个时钟周期
for l2 and then there's an additional
为L2，然后有一个附加
Costas so you always have to pay the hit
科斯塔斯所以你 总是要付出的命中
time right the hit time is the best you
时间正确的命中 时间是最好的你
can do but if you have a Miss then it's
可以做，但如果你有一个小姐那么 它的
you pay the hit time because you have to
你付出的命中时间，因为你必须
do the search and eventually you're
做搜索，最终你
going to return the word back to the
要回返回字到
requester but you have this additional
请求者但你有这样的附加
cost which you have to go which is going
你必须去这是怎么回事成本
to the memory to fetch the data okay so
在 内存获取数据那么好
that that missed penalty that's so
这是罚失点球是 如此
called miss penalty is on the order of
所谓的未中损失的量级
hundreds of cycles for main memory but
数百周期的主内存 ，但是
in other levels of the hierarchy it can
在层次结构中它可以 与其他各级
be huge so the miss penalty if you if
是巨大的，因此 命中 损失，如果你要是
you have a cache in main memory
你必须在主内存中缓存
that's caching blocks that are stored on
这是上 存储 的缓存块
disk the the miss penalty is enormous
磁盘的 缺失 损失是巨大的
so it's kind of interesting if you think
所以这是很有趣，如果你认为
about it that performance is the
关于 它 的 性能是该
performance of these systems is very
这些系统的性能是非常
sensitive to the miss rate much more
在 命中 率更 敏感
sensitive than you would think and in
敏感的比你想象中和
fact 99% hit rate is twice as good as a
事实上99％的命中率的两倍，一个好
97% hit rate yes yeah they hit so the
97％的命中率是啊，他们打这样
question is does the hit time include
问题是不命中的时间包括：
the time tax to access the tag and yes
时间税访问标记是的
so the hit time is the time it takes to
所以命中时间 是花费的时间
to search to determine if that item is
搜索以确定该产品
is is in the cache and then return it
是在缓存中， 然后返回它
so basically we'll use it a title
所以基本上我们将使用 一个标题
property yeah so the yeah so the the
财产是啊所以啊 所以在
Miss the Miss penalty is the time it
小姐小姐 点球是 一次
takes for the cash to fetch the data
花费的 现金来获取数据
from memory so that's all the latency
从内存中，因此这一切的等待时间
you know going across the buses the time
你知道整个大巴去的时间
it takes the memory to respond to the
它占用内存向响应
requests the time he takes the data to
要求 他取得数据的 时间
flow back over the buses back to the the
流回了公交车回 了
cache so the time for a Miss is going to
缓存等了小姐的时间将会
be the hit time plus the Miss penalty
是命中时间加上 罚小姐
that clear
说清楚
so I mean imagine suppose there's a hit
所以我的意思是想象假设有命中目标
time of one cycle and a Miss penalty of
一个周期的时间和 一个小姐罚
100 cycles that those are reasonable
100个循环，这些是合理
numbers so the average access access
号码，使平均存取 访问
time if you have 97% hits it's the hit
时间，如果你有 97％的命中是命中
time plus the percentage of misses times
时间加上未命中次数的百分比
the Miss penalty so that's four cycles
小姐罚所以这 四个周期
for the average access time but if we
对于平均 访问时间，但如果我们
just increase the the hit rate by two
只是增加两个 命中率
percent the average access time drops by
％的平均访问时间减少
50 percent a factor of two
50％ 的二分之一
all right so why why is this stuff
没事为什么这是为什么东西
important why why should you care about
重要的为什么你为什么要 在乎
it so cash is that we as we've seen are
它使 现金是我们正如我们所看到的
these they're automatic they're all
这些他们自动他们都
built in hardware there's no part of the
内置的硬件有没有的部分
sort of the visible instruction set that
排序可见的指令集，
lets you manipulate caches and you're
让你能够操作的缓存和你
somewhere between codons programs so
密码子计划 ，使 两者之间
that it all happens behind the scenes
这一切都发生在幕后
automatically in hardware but if you
自动在硬件 ，但如果你
know how care if you know about the
懂得 关心，如果您知道 有关
existence of caches and you have this
缓存的存在，你有这
general idea of how you can work how
你可以是如何工作的总体思路 如何
they work then you can write code that's
他们的工作，那么你可以编写代码 的
cash friendly in the sense that your
现金 在这个意义上 友好的 ，你的
code will have a higher higher miss rate
代码将有更高的高命中率
than code that that isn't cash friendly
比代码未 兑现友好
so the idea is to you want to focus on
这样的想法是要重点关注
making the common case go fast don't
使得常见的情况走快不
spend your time on code that sort of
把时间花在 代码之类的
code that doesn't get execute very much
代码没有得到执行非常
so look at look at the most commonly
所以看一下最常用
called functions and then within those
调用的函数，然后 内的那些
functions look at the inner loop to
功能看内环到
those functions because it's the inner
这些功能，因为它是内
loops that are executing the most right
正在执行最右边的环
so you can as a first approximation you
这样你就可以作为第一近似你
can just ignore sort of stuff if you
可以忽略那种东西，如果你
have nested loops you can ignore stuff
嵌套的循环，你可以忽略 的东西
that's going on in the outer loops and
这是怎么回事外循环和
just focus on the code in the inner loop
只着眼于代码在内部循环
now what you want to do is try to
现在你想要做的是尽力
minimize the misses in the inner loop
最小化在内部循环的未命中
okay so repeated references to a
好了，所以多次提到一个
variable is variables are good
变量是变量都不错
especially if those are local variables
特别是如果这些是局部 变量
right so remember if you declare a local
右所以记住 ，如果你声明 一个局部
variable and see the compiler can put
变量看编译器可以把
that in a register right if you're
为寄存器中的权利，如果你是
referencing global variables maybe not
引用全局变量也许不是
the compiler doesn't know what's going
编译器不知道是怎么回事
on so it can't put that rough it can't
上所以 不能把那粗糙的它不能
put the reference to that variable in a
把参考以该变量
C in a register okay so repeated
下， 在 寄存器还好如此反复
references to local variables stored on
对局部变量的引用存储在
the stack are good because those will
堆栈是一件好事 ，因为那些会
get turned into register accesses you'll
得到变成寄存器访问你
never go to memory okay also stride one
从来不去内存也没关系 一个迈进
accesses two arrays are good
访问两个数组 都不错
and they're good because of the
而且他们因为良好
existence of these blocks right so the
这些块的生存权利，因此
only way you'd know that stride one
只有这样，你会知道 ，一个箭步
references our good is if you knew that
引用我们的好是，如果 你知道
caches have the 64-byte blocks okay so
高速缓存具有64字节数据块好了，所以
they and strive one one reference will
他们力争一个 一个参考会
have half the Miss rate as a stride to
有小姐率一大步，一半
reference because if you're doing stride
引用，因为如果你做 步幅
one references the first reference to a
一个引用第一参照
word in a block will miss but then
字块会错过，但随后
subsequent references will hit right and
后续引用会打右
you'll hit if you're doing a stride one
如果你正在做一个箭步一个 ，你会打
reference you're going to hit every
参考你要每打
every word in that block if your drive
在该块 ，如果 你的 驱动器的每一个字
if you're doing stride two references
如果你正在做跨步 两个引用
you're only going to hit every other
你只是打隔日
word right so you'll only get you get
字右所以你只能得到你
sort of half the so you'll missed at
排序的一半，所以你会 在错过
twice the rate so the basically the
两倍的速度，因此基本上
point I want to make you is that our
点我要让你的是， 我们的
understanding of caches allow us to sort
缓存的理解让 我们整理
of quantify this this qualitative notion
的 量化这定性这个概念
of locality that we developed the last
局部性的，我们开发的最后
time right the last time we looked at we
时间右边的最后一次看我们
said if it's doing stride one references
说，如果它做跨步一个引用
that's good if it's if we're doing if
这是很好的，如果是，如果我们做的，如果
we're accessing the same variable over
我们访问了相同的变量
and over that's good but if we
并在这很好，但如果我们
understand caches now we can quantify it
了解缓存现在我们可以 量化它
in terms of miss rate all right so let's
在命中率方面没事让我们
finish up the rest of the class we're
完成了我们是班上的 其他同学
going to look at the performance impact
要看看对 性能 的 影响
of caches on your code okay and why why
您的代码行不行，为什么，为什么缓存
you need why you need to know about
你需要你为什么需要知道
these things and that the impact that
这些东西和造成的影响
they can have so there's a very
他们能有那么有一个很
interesting function that's actually
有趣的功能，这 实际上 是
plotted on the cover of your your text
绘制你的文本封面
book that we call the memory Mountain I
书中 ， 我们称之为记忆山我
learned about this from a graduate
得知这个情况从研究生
student here at Carnegie Mellon back in
这里的学生在卡内基梅隆回
the 90s so you develop this notion there
上世纪90年代，所以你发展这个概念有
Tom Stricker and what it is that say the
汤姆·斯特里克 和它是什么 ， 说
memory Mountain plots a measure called
内存山地块名为措施
read through put or read bandwidth which
通过放或读取带宽 读取 哪个
is the number of bytes read from memory
从存储器中 读取的字节 数
so if you have four
所以，如果你有四个
have a loop and you're scanning over a
有一个循环，你要扫描过
vector so you have a vector of say say
矢量让你有发言权的向量发言权
double words and you're reading those
双字和你 读那些
elements from a vector one after the
从一个 向量中的一个元件之后的
other the read throughput is the number
其他的读取吞吐量是多少
of megabytes per second that you can
兆字节每秒， 你可以
that you can perform that task at and
您可以在执行这个任务，
the memory mountian plots read
内存地块殷海涛读
throughput as a function of the temporal
吞吐量时间的函数
and spatial locality in that loop okay
在该循环空间局部性好吗
so in a sense it's looking at a wide
因此，在某种意义上，它在看一个宽
range of locality options or
的局部性选项范围或
characteristics in a program and it's
在程序的特点和它的
plotting the performance of that memory
绘图内存的性能
system on that across that range is a
系统上跨该范围是
two-dimensional function so in some ways
二维 功能，因此在某些方面
the memory Mountain is a kind of a
内存山是一类的
fingerprint right every system has its
指纹右每个系统 都有它的
own unique memory Mountain that we can
自己独特的记忆山， 我们可以
measure right by writing a simple
通过编写 一个简单的衡量权
program and so the idea here is that to
程序和这样的想法在这里是 要
construct the memory Mountain we write a
构建存储山 我们写了一个
program called test
程序调用测试
shoot
射击
for some reason it's not okay all right
由于某种 原因，这不是没事 没事
so we believe when we build a memory
因此，我们相信，当 我们建立了一个记忆
Mountain we're given a vector that
山 我们给出一个向量
consists of a collection of double words
由双字的集合
and then we write a loop that reads
然后我们写一个循环，读取
those words that read some number of
那些阅读一定数量的话
words in this case
在这种情况下的话
there we go so it reads it reads Elam's
我们走，所以它读取它 读取 埃兰之
number of elements right so we've got
元素个数权利，使我们有
each of these double word elements with
每个与这些双字元件
a stride of stride okay so if we have a
步幅 一个箭步 好了，如果我们有 一个
stride of one I know those kind of
一大步，我知道那些 种
redundant him so if we have a stride of
冗余他 ，所以，如果我们有一个箭步
one then we'll we'll have our loop
一个那么我们将我们将有我们的 环
wheels will sort of loop through and
车轮将整理 循环 的 通过和
read these elements until we've read
阅读这些内容，直到我们读过
elements number of those elements okay
这些元素中的元素数目没关系
and then we'll do it again and then that
然后我们将再次和那么做
warms up the cache then we do it again
升温缓存，然后我们再做一次
and do exactly the same thing so if
做 同样的事情，所以如果
we're doing this with a stride of two
我们有两个一个箭步这样做
then we will be reading we would read
然后我们会阅读我们会读
this word zero or LM - LM 4 and so on
这个词零或LM - LM 4 等
okay so well then what all we're doing
好吧 ，那好吧，我们正在做什么都
we're just for wide range of strides and
我们只是 为广泛的进步和
a wide range of sizes we're scanning
尺寸范围广泛的，我们要扫描
over this vector and just recording how
在这个矢量，只是记录如何
long it takes to do that read and then
多长时间才能做到这一点读，然后
convert we convert that into megabytes
转换我们转换到这一点兆字节
per second and in order to I just wanted
每秒以我只是想
to show you this this is we don't need
给你看这个，这是我们不需要
we're not going to go into detail about
我们不打算深究细节
this but this is actually how I
这一点，但 其实 这是 我怎么
generated the the cover on the book and
所产生的对本书的封面和
in order to in order to use to exploit
为了才能使用利用
the parallelism inside the intel
英特尔内部的并行
processor like you learned about last
像你这样的 处理器 了解过去
week there's there's a lot of parallel
本周有有很多 平行的
functional units in order to exploit
为了利用功能单元
those i i i did 4x4 loop unrolling so
这些III做四轮驱动循环展开 等等
I'm actually doing sort of four scans in
我实际上做那种四个在扫描
parallel but the general idea is just
平行，但总的想法是只
what I've showed you here and this this
我在这里向您展示，和本
4x4 this 4x4 loop unrolling is just an
4×4×4这个循环的展开仅仅是一个
optimization but I wanted to show it to
优化但我想展示给
you because it actually it's the exact
你，因为它 实际上它的确切
same
相同
principles you learned about last week
原理你了解了上周
when Professor Brian talked about code
当布赖恩教授谈到码
optimization so what we do is we we call
优化所以我们做的是我们我们称之为
this test function with these various
这些不同这个测试功能
ranges of Elam's and stride and then we
埃兰之和步幅，那么我们的范围
measure the performance and we get this
衡量性能， 我们得到这个
beautiful picture this beautiful
美丽的图画这个美丽
function to me it's beautiful I don't
功能对我来说它的美丽我 不
know is it look beautiful to you so on
知道是看美女 ，你等
the Z our z axis is plotting read
在Z我们的Z轴正密谋读
throughput in megabytes per second
吞吐量每秒兆字节
ranging from 2000 megabytes per second
范围从 每秒2000兆
up to 16,000 megabytes per second this
这种 每秒高达16,000兆字节
this axis is measuring is stride
该轴是测量是步幅
so going from stride 1 up to stride 12
从步幅1所以往上走阔步12
and this axis is so as we as we increase
这轴，以便我们为我们增加
stride we're decreasing the spatial
步幅我们降低空间
locality all right
当地没事
and this axis is the size axis so we're
这轴是尺寸轴所以我们
going from I think 16 K up to 128
去从我认为16K的多达128个
megabytes so this is the number of
兆所以这是多少
elements we're going to read each pass
我们要读 通每一个 元素
through so as we as we increase the size
通过这样，我们为我们增加 的 大小
we're sort of decreasing the impact of
我们有点下降的影响
temporal locality because work as we
时间局部性因为工作 ，因为我们
increase the size there's fewer and
加大尺寸 有越来越
fewer caches in our hierarchy can hold
在我们的 层次 较少的高速缓存 可以容纳
all that data and so this so we've got
所有这些数据， 因此这使我们有
spatial locality decreasing in this
空间局部性这一下降
direction and temporal locality
方向和时间局部性
decreasing in this direction so as a
减少了该方向 ，从而一
programmer what you want to do you want
程序员，你想要做什么，你想
to be up here right good spatial
要在这里正确的良好的空间
locality good temporal locality because
当地良好的时间局部性，因为
you can get like 14 gigabytes per second
你可以像每秒14千兆字节
measure Greek throughput you don't want
衡量你不希望 希腊吞吐量
to be down here which is only about 100
要到这里这 是只有约100
megabytes per second where you're
兆字节每秒你在哪里
reading out of memory right so the
读出 的内存权，因此
difference between reading all of your
阅读完所有的差异你
data from memory and we or reading it
从 内存中，我们或阅读它 的数据
from some part of the the caches is huge
从的某些部分高速缓存是巨大的
it's enormous
这是 巨大的
ok so because you're 213 students you'll
确定这样 ，因为你是213级的学生，你会
be up here and all the students that
是在这里，所有的学生们
didn't take 213 they'll be down here and
没拿213，他们会到 这里和
I've actually had I've actually had
其实我已经有我其实是有
people several people write back to tell
人 几个人写回来告诉
me about their experiences you know in
我自己的经历，你知道
internships and jobs after they lost an
实习和就业机会，他们失去了 一个后
emu where they were given some code that
鸸鹋在那里他们得到 了一些代码，
that was down here and they recognized
这是到这里，这才认出
the locality issues and they got it
局部性问题，但他们得到了它
you know better up here or close at
你知道更好地在这里或 在 接近
least better
好至少
so this this picture this so-called
所以这本图画这个所谓的
memory mountain has all kinds of
内存 山上有各种
interesting features first of all
有趣的功能首先是
there's these what I call ridges of
有这就是我所说的脊
temporal locality where these ridges see
时间局部性其中，这些脊见
these Ridge lines if you think of this
这些脊线，如果你认为这
is like a mountain you see this
就像你看到的这一座山
Ridgeline and you see this Ridgeline and
山脊线， 你会看到这个 山脊线和
here's another ridge line and then
这里的另一个脊线， 然后
here's a here's another one these
这里有一个在这里的另外一个这些
correspond to different levels in the
对应于不同的水平在
hierarchy so this this top Ridgeline is
层次所以这此之上 棱线
where you're reading directly out of l1
在那里你直接读出 L1的
and it should be perfectly flat and it's
它应该是完全平坦的 ，它的
so fast that we're getting like
如此之快，我们得到像
measurement jitter performance jitter
测量抖动性能抖动
right but it's it's and this little
正确的，但它是和这个小
drop-off here is a measurement artifact
下车这里是一个测量伪影
it it should it shouldn't be there
它应该不应该在那里
should be it should be flat and go all
应该是它应该是平的，全力以赴
the way to the wall back here and then
一直到墙上回到这里，然后
here this this ridge line is where we're
这里本该山脊线就是我们
accessing l2 this is what we're
访问L2这就是我们
accessing l3 and and here's what we're
访问L3 和这里就是我们
accessing mostly from memory so you have
从内存访问主要是让你拥有
these ridges of temporal locality and
时间局部性的这些山脊 和
then you have these slopes of decreasing
那么你有减少这些斜坡
spatial locality so you see the slope
空间位置，所以你看到的斜率
here as work so as we're moving from the
这里工作 ，以便我们从移动
from the top of the slope down to the
从斜坡的顶部向下到
bottom we're decreasing our spatial
底部我们减少我们的空间
locality so we're getting less benefit
本地所以我们越来越少的好处
for these blocks that we're bringing in
对于这些块，我们正在引进
right so you can see the we're getting
正确的，所以你可以看到我们得到
less benefit out of the cost that we
少了成本效益， 我们
went through of importing of fetching
通过导入 取 的 去了
these blocks and once the stride hits
这些块一旦步幅命中
the block size now every reference is
块大小现在每个引用是
hitting a different block and so and
击中不同的块，因此和
then it flattens out then you get you're
那么它变平，那么你得到你
getting nose benefit from spatial
正从鼻子空间受益
locality and similarly here is where
局部性和同样这里是哪里
this this this slope is where we're
这这这斜率就是我们
reading from l3 and and and it flattens
从L3阅读和与它变平
out always if they always flatten out at
总是出来，如果他们总是变平的
the at the block size which is a stride
所述块的大小是一个步幅
these are double words right so it's
这些都是双字右所以它的
stride of 8
8步幅
is 64 bytes so once you exceed a stride
为64个字节，因此，一旦你超过了一大步
of eight then you're no longer you're
八，然后你不再是 你
missing every time in it in a different
缺少它，每次在不同的
block and there's this interesting this
块有这个有趣的这个
one puzzled me for a while
一个困扰了我一段时间
you might be wondering like how come
你可能想知道怎么样来
like over here as we increase the size
像在这里，我们增加大小
we can sort of we're sort of getting the
我们可以排序的我们有点获得
we're sort of as we increase the size
我们都有点像 我们增加大小
we're doing most of our references out
我们正在做 我们的大部分引用了
of caches that are lower in the cache
缓存是在缓存中低
hierarchy but except when we're doing
层次结构，但是当我们正在做的，除了
stride one references you can see all
迈进一个参考，你可以看到所有
the way up to right at the end right
一直到正确的到底对不对
before it exceeds the size of l3 it's
超过 L3的大小 之前 它的
flat okay
平好吗
and it's it's running at the l2 rate and
和它的它的运行在L2率和
so here's the l1 rate and then it drops
所以这里的L1速率，然后再下降
off and then it's running at a constant
关闭， 然后它运行 在一个恒定
l2 rate until the data no longer sits in
L2率， 直到数据不再 坐
l3 so I think what's going on here is
L3 所以我觉得这是 怎么回事 上是
that the hardware the cache the cache
在 硬件缓存缓存
the l2 cache hardware is recognizing or
L2高速缓存硬件识别 或
maybe it's an l1 but some some some
也许这是一个L1但一些一些一些
logic in that in the cache system is
逻辑， 在 所述高速缓冲存储器系统 是
recognizing the stride one reference
识别步幅一个参考
pattern because it sees all the
模式，因为它 认为所有的
addresses it's wrecked it's recognizing
地址它破坏了它的识别
that stride one pattern and then it's
该步幅一个模式，那么它的
aggressively prefetching from l3 into l2
从L3积极预取到L2
so that those so it's such an ahead of
使那些因此它是这样一个提前
time it's anticipating it saying look
一次它预计 它 说看
I've gotten five stride one references
我已经得到了5个步幅 一个引用
in a row I'm going to go grab a whole
在一排我要去抓住一个整体
bunch of blocks and load them all up
块的串 并加载它们都起来
because by the principle of spatial
因为空间的原则
locality those blocks those blocks are
当地那些块的块
going to be referenced in the near
要在 不久 的被引用
future so this was really neat and this
未来所以这 是很整洁，这
only happened within the last couple
只有最后几内发生
years so the Intel engineers are always
年使英特尔的工程师总是
hard at work and maybe by the time the
努力工作，也许通过时间
time we do the next the next edition of
时间我们做的 下一下一 版
the memory mountain those systems will
内存 山上那些系统会
recognize stride 2 and you know other
认识步幅2，你知道其他
stride patterns too but from this data
步幅模式 太多，但此 数据
it appears that it's only recognizing
看来，它的唯一识别
stride 1
跨度1
okay so you can real we can improve the
好了，你可以 真正的，我们可以 提高
spatial and temporal locality of our
的空间和时间局部性我们
programs in several different ways that
几种不同的方法程序，
one way to improve the spatial locality
改善空间局部性的一种方式
is to rearrange loops and I'll use
是重新排列循环和我将使用
matrix multiplication as an example so
矩阵乘法作为一个例子，以便
here's a sort of a simple matrix
这里有一种简单的矩阵
multiplication in code where we're
乘法在代码中我们
multiplying a times B and adding it
相乘的次B 和将其添加
we're taking what's in of the IJ element
我们正在采取 什么在IJ元素
of C and then to that we're adding the
的C，然后给我们增加了
sum the inner product of row I of a and
总结的一排我 的内积
the row J a column J of B okay and then
行j 行，然后 B的J列
so we're going through and for each IJ
所以我们要通过和每个IJ
in this matrix C we're computing an
在这个矩阵C我们计算 的
inner product and then creating that sum
内积，然后创建总和
so we can actually turns out there's a
所以我们实际上可以证明有一个
lot of different ways to do matrix
很多不同的方式 做矩阵
multiply and this is we can permute
乘，这是我们可以置换
these these loops in any of six
这些这些循环中的任何六个
different possible permutations so this
不同的可能的排列所以这
is a permutation where it's I followed
是置换它是我跟着
by J followed by K but five other
用j，其后为K 而其他五个
possibilities are feasible and so we can
可能性是可行的，所以我们可以
actually analyze those those different
其实分析这些不同的那些
permutations and predict which one will
排列预测哪一个
have the best performance okay so what
有好了，所以什么是最好的性能
we'll do is we'll look at the inner loop
我们要做的是，我们将看看内环
and we'll look at the access pattern of
我们将看看的访问 模式
the inner loops and since the access
内环路， 因为接入
pattern on arrays C a and D
在 阵列 上 ℃ 的和 D图案
okay so let's look at the ijk
好了，让我们来看看IJK
implementation that I just showed you so
实现时，我刚才给你看这么
as always we focus on the inner loop and
一如既往，我们专注于内环 和
if you notice this inner loop is doing a
如果您发现该内环是做了
row wise access of column a and a column
排列和列的明智访问
wise access I'm sorry a row wise access
明智的访问对不起连续明智访问
of array a and column wise access of a
阵列的和的列明智访问的
row B so row wise of a column wise of B
列B因此行明智明智B的柱的
we don't really care about C because
我们真的不关心C，因为
it's out it's not in the inner loop okay
它的出它不是在内环好吗
so just ignore that so given our
所以才忽略了 这样给我们的
assumption that we can hold in this case
假设我们能在这种情况下举行
we're assuming that we can hold for four
我们 假设， 我们 可以 容纳四
of these integer elements in a in one
在这些整数元素在一个
block so the row wise access which has
块，其中有行明智访问
good spatial locality will miss one
良好的空间局部性会错过一个
every four accesses okay the very first
每四个访问没关系最先
reference will miss and then the next
参考将无缘再下
three will hit and then the next
三会打再 下
reference after that will hit a new
参考后将创出新
block okay so so one out of four
块好了，所以四个这样一出
references to a will miss but because
到引用将错过，但因为
the access pattern for B is column wise
对于B的访问模式是逐列
every every every reference to B will
每每每个引用到B将
miss okay so the average number of
错过好所以平均数
misses per loop iteration is one point
每循环迭代未命中是一个点
two five okay the j iik version is
两个五 好第j IIK 版本
exactly the same pattern
完全一样的模式
kij is a little different here we're
KIJ在这里有一点不同我们
doing row-wise access of b and a row
做B和A行 的逐行访问
wise access of c so that's good right so
的C明智访问，因此这是很好的权利，使
now we've got stride one accesses on
现在我们已经有了一个箭步上访问
both BMC and the reference to a is
既BMC和参照 本发明的IS
outside of the loop so we don't care
在循环之外 ，所以我们 不关心
about it so so both B and C will miss
它那么那么B和C将缺席
one quarter of the time okay so the
时间的四分之一好吗 所以
total average number of misses per loop
平均数量总每循环未命中
iteration will be 0.5 that's pretty good
迭代将是0.5就不错了
and I KJ has the same similar behavior
我KJ具有相同的类似行为
now jki is sort of the exact opposite
现在JKI是那种完全相反的
jki does column-wise access of a and
JKI做 的逐列访问和
column wise access of c so right we know
章 C所以正确的，我们知道 逐列访问
that's a stinker
这是一个臭气熏天
right and and we qualitatively know it's
右，我们定性地知道它的
bad and we can compute that it will miss
糟糕，我们可以计算， 它就会错过
a one time per loop iteration so that
每次循环迭代，这样一个时间
will be two total of two misses per
将有两个总每2个未命中
iteration and kji has the same bad
迭代和KJI具有相同的坏
pattern okay so if we look at all these
模式好了，所以，如果我们 看一下 所有这些
permutations you can see that ijk and ji
排列你可以看到，IJK 和JI
k miss 1.25 has 1.25 mrs. K IJ has 0.5
ķ错过1.25 1.25有太太。 ķIJ有0.5
misses and j ki has two misses so
缺失和斯基有两个失误使
clearly it looks like ki J and its
显然，它看起来像 きJ和其
brethren are the best option the only
弟兄们是最好的选择的唯一
difference is that K ki J has this
差 中 Kきj具有这
additional store so there might be a
额外的存储 ，以便有可能是一个
question that is that going to create is
问题那就是 要创造是
that going to slow things down well it
这将放慢改革的步伐以及它
turns out in systems and any kind
原来， 在系统和任何种类
storage systems rights are much easier
存储系统的权利更 容易
to deal with them reads can it can you
对付他们可以读取它可以你
think about why that might be true so
想想为什么，可能是真的如此
right you have a lot more flexibility
对你有更多的 灵活性
than you do with Ruiz
比你做鲁伊斯
I mean yes
我的意思是
that's exactly so you can have options
这正是让你可以有选择
you can do you can write back defer you
你可以做你可以写回 你推迟
can defer writing until the value the
可以推迟写作，直到 值
value that your written is actually used
你写的实际使用值
but when you read an item you're stuck
但是当你看一个项目 你被困
you can't do anything until until you
你不能做什么，直到，直到 你
get that data so it turns out that that
获得这些数据，以便事实证明，这
rights don't really that this additional
权利并不真的那么这种额外
store doesn't really hurt us and so when
店内并没有真正伤害我们，所以当
we measure these on a modern system you
我们衡量这些现代化的系统，你上
can see that the the Kate kij which has
可以看出 ， 凯特 KIJ 其中有
the the fewest number of misses has you
在数量最少的失误有你
see we're getting like one miss Oh what
看到我们正在像一个错过 哦 什么
we're plotting here is cycles per inner
我们在这里密谋为每内循环
loop iteration so each each iteration is
循环迭代所以每次每次迭代是
taking about one cycle which is really
取约一个 周期，这是真的
good this i JK pattern which is kind of
好这个 我JK模式这是一种
the intermediate 1.2 misses that's sort
中间1.2惦记这是排序
of in between and the JK I which has two
在之间和JK 我 有两个
misses per iteration is the worst ok so
每次迭代失误是最糟糕的确定，所以
what's interesting is we could actually
有趣的是，我们 居然 可以
just by doing a little bit of analysis
只是做 分析 的一点点
simple analysis we could actually
简单的分析，我们实际上可能
predict what this what this graph would
预测这是什么这是什么图形会
look like ok in the in left last 10
看起来像确定在离开最后的 10
minutes of the class we're going to look
该类分钟 ，我们要 看看
at how to improve temporal locality now
在如何提高 现在 时间局部性
so what we did with with when we
所以我们所做的事情与我们
rearranged our loops in the matrix
重新安排我们的循环 中的矩阵
multiplication what we were doing was in
乘法我们在做什么是
improving our spatial locality right but
改善我们的空间局部性的权利 ，但
we didn't we didn't really do anything
我们没有，我们没有做任何事情
to improve the temporal locality to
以 提高时间局部性来
improve temporal locality you have to
提高时间局部性你必须
use a technique called blocking and this
使用称为阻断技术和本
is important to understand because
重要的是要理解 ，因为
you're going to need it in your cache
你会需要它的缓存
lab for one thing but it's also a very
实验室的一两件事，但它也是一个非常
general technique anytime you need any
一般的技术 ，任何时候你需要的任何
time you're having issues with temporal
时间您遇到问题的 时间
locality okay so we're not going to go
地方好了，所以我们不会去
into too much detail this code but what
太多的细节这个代码，但什么
I did I rewrote the matrix multiply so
我做了我重写了矩阵乘法 等等
that it operates you know a
它运行你知道
two-dimensional matrix that you can
二维 矩阵，你可以
really just think of it as a contiguous
真的只是把它作为一个连续
array of bytes so I just rewrote this
字节数组，所以我只是重写了这个
code to operate on a contiguous array
码到一个连续阵列上操作
one-dimensional array and then I'm doing
一维 数组，然后我做
the indexing explicitly here so here at
索引明确这里这么在这里
CI x then plus J
CI X然后 加Ĵ
this is an n-by-n matrix what I'm doing
这是一个 N-n 矩阵 我 在做 什么
is I'm I'm accessing the I'm computing
是我，我 访问我的计算
where the I throw starts and then I'm
当 我扔开始，然后我
going to the J column of that row and
去 该 行 的第j列 ，
then accessing that element all right so
然后访问该元素的所有权利，使
let's but it's the same idea as before
让我们但它是相同的思路前
so let's look at the Miss rate for this
所以让我们看看命中率本
this is just our original this is our
这 只是我们原来这是我们的
original unblocked matrix multiply so
原始未封端矩阵相乘，从而
what we're doing is we're we're
我们正在做的是我们是我们
computing C 0 0 and we're doing that by
计算C 0 0和我们正在做的 ，通过
taking an inner product of row 0 and
取0 行 的内积 和
column 0 oops so if you look at the
列0哎呀所以如果你看一下
we're assuming that the cache the cache
我们假定缓存缓存
blocks holds eight doubles and that the
块拥有八个双打，而且
matrix elements are doubles then we're
矩阵要素的双打然后我们
going to miss one eighth of the time
会想念时八分之一
okay so in the first iteration we're
好了，所以在第一次迭代我们
going to miss the first iteration does
要 错过第一次迭代做
any of these things
这些事情
and since we're missing n over eight at
而且，由于我们在缺少ñ超过八
the time what we're missing one block
就是我们缺少一个块的时间
for every eight eight references for
对于每八八引用
each for the first iteration we're going
对于每一个 我们将 第一次迭代
to miss n over eight and since there's n
错过ñ超过八和因为n值
for each element for each block I'm
对于每个块，我的每个元素
sorry and then oh so this is the number
对不起，然后哦，所以这是 多少
of blocks and the number of misses and
块和未命中的数目和
then we have n elements so that the
那么我们有n个元素，使得
total number of misses is nine over n
未命中的总数为 九 在 n
divided by eight misses for the first
八次错过分为 第一
iteration okay the second iteration will
迭代还好第二次迭代会
have the same number of misses because
具有相同数量的失误， 因为
of our assumptions about the the size of
我们约的大小假设
this array so this these rows are way
此数组所以这个 这些行 是这样
too big to fit in the cache so we never
太大，不适合在高速缓存中 ，所以我们从来没有
get any we don't get any temporal
得到任何我们没有得到任何时间
locality okay so the total number of
地方好了，所以总数
misses is nine n over eight times the
失误是9种N超过八倍
number of elements that we're updating
元素的数量，我们正在 更新
which is N squared okay so our total
这是N 的平方 好了，我们的总
misses is nine over eight times and
失误是九的8倍 和
and in cubed now let's rewrite the code
在现在立方，让我们重写代码
to use blocking and so you can look at
使用阻塞，所以你可以看看
this code later but it's much simpler
此代码后，但它更简单
just to just to look at it pictorially
只是，只是看它 形象地
so what what we're doing instead of
所以我们在做什么，而不是
updating one element at a time we're
同时 ，我们正在更新一个元素
updating a sub block a B by B sub block
更新的子块由B子块中的乙
and we're doing that just totally
和我们正在做的，只是完全
analogously to when our original case
类似于当我们 最初的情况下，
where B equal one this this B by B sub
其中B等于1这个这个乙通过B子
block in C is computed by taking an
在C中的块是通过取一个计算
inner product of the sub blocks of a set
一组的子块的内积
of sub blocks in a with a set of sub
在与一组子的子块的
blocks in B and for each one of those
在B 和这些 中的 每一个块
we're doing a little mini matrix
我们正在做的一点点小矩阵
multiplication so we're taking we're
乘法，所以我们正在做我们
taking this sub block times this sub
采取这种分块次此子
block plus the second sub block of a
块加的第二子块
times the second sub block of of B plus
倍的B的第二子块加
the third sub block of a times the third
一个 倍第三 的第三子块
sub block of B and so on okay so we're
B的子块等等好了 ，所以我们
doing the same inner product operation
做相同的内积运算
but instead of scalars we're doing it
但不是标量，我们正在做的
with these little sub these little tiny
与这些小亚这些一点微小
matrices okay all right so let's look at
矩阵还好没事那么让我们来看看
let's look at what happens to the Miss
让我们看看会发生什么情况 小姐
rate when we do this so there's there's
速度，我们这样做的时候那么有有
n over B blocks in in any row or column
Ñ在B嵌段在任何行或列中
and since there's B squared items in
并且因为有'S B方在项目
each block B times B there's B squared
每块B乘以B有'S B平方
over eight misses for each block okay
超过八错过 每个块行不行
and so then and then since there's
等再然后因为有
there's n over B blocks in each matrix
有n值超过B 嵌段中的每个矩阵
and there's two matrices there's 2 - n
并有两个矩阵有 2 - N的
over B times B squared over 8 misses for
在B个时间乙平方超过8个为未命中
this first iteration so that that works
这第一次迭代，使得工作
out to be an NB divided by 4 and the
出 要一个 NB 4 和分
second iteration has the same as the
第二迭代具有一样的
same miss sort of same miss rate so that
同样错过排序相同的命中率，这样的
the total number of misses is the number
未命中的总数是多少
of the number of misses for each
未命中的每个数
iteration x times the number of elements
元件 的迭代x倍的数量
and see that we're updating okay which
看看我们正在更新其没关系
is n over B squared so that all works
为n 乙级以上平方，使 所有作品
out - it's still in its n cube divided
出来-它仍然在其N立方分
by 4 B so in our first case with no
通过4 B因此，在我们的第一种情况下，没有
blocking although that the number of
阻断尽管该数目
misses is asymptotically the same but
失误是渐近相同的，但
there's this pretty this big difference
有这个漂亮的这个大的差异
in the constant factor so for no
在常数因子所以没有
blocking it's 9 over 8 for blocking it's
阻止它的9超过8阻止它的
1 over 4b we're now we can we can just
1超过40亿，我们现在是我们可以，我们可以只
sort of drive that down by by increasing
那种开车下来通过增加
the block size so this gives us some
块大小，因此这给了我们一些
some control but we still we have we
一些控制，但我们还是我们，我们
can't make the block the blocks too big
不能使块的块太大
because we need to fit three blocks in
因为我们需要放到三个块
the in cash at any one point in time
在现金在任何一个时间点
okay so the reason this is a dramatic
好了，所以 这种 情况的 原因 是一个戏剧性的
difference right and the reason for this
区别权利 ，这样做的原因
is that by doing the blocking we're sort
是做 阻挡我们排序
of exploiting once we load a block into
利用一次我们加载一个模块到
memory we're sort of reusing its items
内存我们有点重用其项目
over and over again so we're exploiting
一遍 又一遍 ，所以我们正在开发
more temporal locality and matrix
更多的时间局部性 和矩阵
multiplication has this into this
乘法有这个这个
implicit locality because the
隐地方，因为
computation is order n cubed but the
计算是n阶立方但
size of the data is N squared and so so
的数据的大小是 N的平方和，以便因此
we must be reusing some data items right
我们一定要重用一些数据项权
the problem with our scaler approach is
与我们的缩放方法的问题
that we we were when we were reusing
我们我们，当我们 重新使用 了
them they weren't in the cache okay
他们并不在缓存 好吗
all right so the point that I wanted to
没事让我想点
make with you is that cache memories
让你的是，高速缓冲存储器
although they're they're sort of
虽然他们有几分
built-in automatic hardware
内置自动硬件
storage devices and you can't really
存储设备和你不能真正
control them if you know about them you
控制他们，如果你了解他们，你
can take advantage of your knowledge and
可以把 你 的 知识 优势 ，
exploit exploit them and make your code
开发利用他们，让你的代码
run faster okay and the way you do this
运行速度很好，而且你这样做的方法
is like I said focus on the inner loops
就像我说的重点 放在内循环
do is try to do try to accesses that our
尝试去做做尝试访问我们的
stride one and try to maximize to to
一个迈进，并试图最大限度地 向
maximize spatial locality and try to
最大限度地提高空间局部性，并尝试
maximize temporal locality by reusing
通过最大限度地重用时间局部性
local variables which can then be put
局部变量，然后可以放
into registers okay so that's it for
到寄存器好了，这就是它
today good luck with your attack lab if
今天的好运与你的攻击，如果实验室
you haven't finished it and don't forget
您还没有完成它，不要忘了
to get started on cache labs on this
要获得 高速缓存的实验室就这样 开始 了
weekend
周末